Master.
스승님
There's some progress on another matter.
다소 윤곽이 잡힌 일이 하나 더 있습니다
If the Marquis of Wu'an
만약 무안후가
truly is alive,
정말 살아있다면
what should we do?
어찌하실 겁니까?
That will be a blessing for Great Yin.
그렇다면 대윤의 복이지
There are palace intrigues up ahead
궁 안에선 권력 다툼이 벌어지고
and Prince Changxin's rebellion looming behind.
장신왕이 반란을 일으키려는 이때
The Marquis of Wu'an is a pillar of stability.
무안후가 이 나라의 중심을 잡아 줄 수 있겠지
[Pursuit of Jade]
[축옥]
[Episode 10]
[제10화]
Father,
아버지
Mother.
어머니
Don't cry.
울지 마
Master, who is buried behind this nameless stele?
스승님, 이 이름 없는 무덤의 주인은 누구입니까?
Today is Father's birthday.
오늘 아버지 생신이니
Let's be happy.
기쁜 얼굴을 보여드리자
That way, Father and Mother can be at peace
그래야 하늘에 계신 부모님도
watching us from heaven.
안심하실 거야
Fan Erniu. Meng Lihua.
번이우, 맹이화
Fan...
번씨라...
Could they have been using another surname?
다른 성씨를 쓴 건가?
The current situation is complicated.
지금은 상황이 복잡하게 얽혀있고
So much helplessness lies beneath.
많은 비밀이 숨겨져 있다
When the time is right,
때가 되면
I will tell you everything.
전부 얘기해 주마
It's been 16 years.
16년이나 지났으니
It's time for the truth to come to light.
이제 진실을 밝힐 때도 되었지
Zheng, burn the paper money.
오라버니, 지전을 태워요
There's still some paper money at home.
집에 지전이 좀 남았으니
When we get back, burn some for your parents too.
돌아가서 당신 부모님께도 태워 드려요
Does burning these things...
이런 걸 태우는 게
really work?
정말 소용 있다고 보시오?
Of course.
그럼요
People burn paper money during festivals
사람들이 명절마다 지전을 태우는 건
to tell their deceased loved ones
우리가 아직 그분들을
that we still remember them.
기억하고 있다는 걸 알리기 위해서예요
Wenkan,
문함
promise me one thing.
한 가지 약조하자꾸나
If one day I'm gone,
언젠가 내가 세상을 떠나면
you must take good care of
나 대신
the two Fan sisters for me.
번씨네 두 자매를 잘 보살펴다오
Never let them get involved.
절대 이 일에 휘말리게 해서는 안 돼
Master, you are in such good health.
스승님께서 이렇게 정정하신데
Why say such things?
그게 무슨 말씀입니까?
That day will come.
언젠가 그런 날이 올 테니
Promise me.
약조하거라
I promise you.
명심하겠습니다
Don't burn so much.
한꺼번에 그렇게 많이 태우면 안 돼요
Don't move.
그대로 있어요
♪ The scenery is as clear as me ♪
♪ 이 자연은 나처럼 평온하고 ♪
♪ With very pale colors ♪
♪ 은은한 빛깔은 ♪
♪ Just like the outline in the mirror ♪
♪ 거울에 비친 모습 같아 ♪
♪ I think that's me, being naive ♪
♪ 바보 같은 날 떠올리게 해 ♪
♪ Unlocking my heart ♪
♪ 내 마음 깊은 곳 ♪
♪ I hid you in my soul ♪
♪ 내 영혼에 널 숨겼어 ♪
You two look just like Father and Mother.
오라버니랑 언니 모습이 꼭 아버지랑 어머니 같아요
Thanks.
고맙소
You're welcome.
아니에요
Come, Changning.
이리 와, 장녕
What's wrong with your wrist?
손목을 다쳤소?
The ox cart tipped over when I was collecting pigs yesterday.
어제 돼지를 싣다가 수레가 넘어지는 바람에
I used my hand to break the fall
손으로 받쳤더니
and sprained it.
손목을 삐끗했어요
Changyu's wrist hurts often.
언니 손목은 자주 아파요
Butchering pigs is tiring work.
돼지 잡는 게 엄청 힘들거든요
Constant strain on the wrist over the years can lead to tendon pain.
손목을 자주 쓰면 근육통이 올 수 있소
Luckily the bone isn't affected.
다행히 뼈는 안 다쳤지만
But you need to be careful from now on.
앞으론 조심해야 하오
On the way back later,
돌아가는 길에
I'll get off at the grocery store to buy something.
잡화점에 들러서 살 물건이 있소
You don't have money, right? Here.
돈 있어요? 좀 줄게요
No need. I have some.
괜찮소, 나한테도 있소
How would you have money?
돈이 어디서 났어요?
Get in the cart first.
일단 타시오
Then you two go home first after I'm done shopping.
그럼 물건 사고 나서 두 사람 먼저 집에 가요
I'll go buy you some tangerine peel candy.
난 진피 사탕을 사서 갈게요
Okay.
알았소
Changyu is the best.
언니가 최고야
You...
아니...
People keep dying
서고 골목에서
in Xigu Lane.
자꾸 사람이 죽어 나가는 걸 보니
Maybe we've provoked
무슨 액운이 껴도
some kind of spirit.
단단히 꼈나 보네
It's bad luck.
재수 없게
Exactly.
그러게 말일세
It seems this rice water isn't enough.
쌀뜨물로는 부족한 것 같으니
In a moment,
이따가
I need to find some dry mugwort leaves
말린 쑥잎 좀 찾아서
and hang them on this door.
문에 걸어둬야겠네
Exactly.
그래야겠네
Look at that jinx.
재앙 덩어리 같으니라고
She was actually staring at us.
뭘 쳐다보는 거람?
You're back?
왔어?
What's wrong?
왜 이렇게
You look listless.
기운이 없어?
Why are you all wet?
몸이 다 젖었잖아
The snow was deep. It must have been the snow.
눈이 깊어서 젖었나 봐요
Wait.
잠깐만
Was someone bullying you
누가 뒤에서 수군대면서
and saying bad things about you?
널 괴롭혔지?
Who dares to do that?
누가 감히 제 험담을 하면
I'd knock their teeth out.
아주 이빨을 부러트려 줄 거예요
I'm going to change my clothes.
옷 좀 갈아입고 올게요
[Xigu Lane]
[서고 골목]
Fan Changyu!
번장옥
Come out here! Fan Changyu!
당장 나와, 번장옥
Fan Changyu! You...
번장옥, 너
Fan Changyu,
번장옥
your sister pushed our Hutou
네 동생이 점심에
down the stairs at noon.
우리 호두를 계단에서 밀었어
Look.
이것 좀 봐
He lost two front teeth.
앞니가 두 대나 빠졌잖아
Tell me, what are you going to do about it?
이거 어떡할 거야?
My sister has always been weak.
안 그래도 허약한 내 동생이
Your grandson is years older than her.
자기보다 몇 살이나 더 먹은 호두를 떠밀었다니
How could she possibly push him?
말이 돼요?
Well...
이...
Granny Kang, let's talk this over calmly.
강 할멈, 차분히 얘기하게
You're making a scene in front of the neighbors.
문 앞에서 이러다가 이웃들이 들으면 비웃을 걸세
The Fan family bullied my grandson.
번씨 가족이 내 손자를 괴롭혔는데
Why should I be afraid of being laughed at?
남들 눈이 뭐가 중요한가?
Isn't it normal for kids to have
애들끼리 놀다가
a few bumps and scrapes when they're playing around?
다칠 수도 있지
-Stop shouting. -Whether you have the right
- 소란 피우지 말게 - 할멈 말만 들을 게 아니라
we need to ask Fan Changning first.
내 동생 말도 들어봐야겠어요
Changning, come out.
장녕, 나와
Come out. It's okay.
괜찮으니까 나와 봐
Changning, come here.
장녕, 이리 와
Come.
어서
Changyu wants to ask you something.
언니가 물어볼 것이 있대
Come here.
얼른 와
Come.
자
Let me ask you.
언니가 묻는 말에 대답해
Did you push Hutou?
네가 호두를 밀었어?
Look at that.
저 어린 것이 벌써
Such a little child already knows how to lie.
거짓말을 하는 것 좀 보게
She nodded just now,
처음에는 고개를 끄덕이더니
and now she's shaking her head.
눈 깜짝할 사이에 고개를 젓잖아
Fan Changning, I'm asking you.
번장녕, 대답해
Don't lie.
거짓말하면 안 돼
Lying will make your mouth rot.
거짓말하면 입이 썩어 문드러질 거야
You know that?
알았어?
Get away!
저리 비켜요
How dare you push me!
감히 날 밀어?
Is there no justice left?
세상에 이런 법이 어디 있어?
The Fan family is so arrogant!
번씨 집안이 아주 막 나가는구먼
They made my grandson like this,
내 손자를 이 꼴로 만들어 놓고
and... and she's acting as if she's completely in the right!
뭘 잘했다고 이렇게 당당해?
Stop shouting!
계속 소리 질러 봐요
Alright.
그만하게
See if I will shove your head
계속 소리 지르면
into the swill bucket!
구정물 독에 처박을 줄 알아요
I held back earlier
아까 참아준 건
because I didn't know
우리 가족이 대체
who my family had offended
누구의 노여움을 샀길래
to bring trouble to Xigu Lane.
서고 골목에 화를 입혔는지 그 까닭을 모르기 때문이에요
I feel guilty towards the neighbors,
이웃들에게 미안하게 생각하지만
but I haven't wronged you.
하지만 할멈한테 미안한 건 아니에요
People keep dying in your family these days.
이 집에서 자꾸만 사람이 죽어 나가는 게
Everyone in the lane knows that you jinxed them!
너 때문이라는 걸 이 골목에 모르는 사람 있어?
You and Mrs. Song gossip about me every day.
할멈이랑 송 할멈이 허구한 날 내 뒷담화하는 거
Do you think I don't know?
모를 줄 알아요?
Fine.
좋아요
I'll grant your wish today.
오늘 그 소원 이루어 줄게요
What are you doing?
뭐 하는 거야?
The neighbors are watching.
이웃들이 보고 있는데
Do you dare commit violence here?
여기서 무슨 짓을 저지르려고?
You've already ruined my reputation.
어차피 두 사람 때문에 이미 평판이 바닥에 떨어졌는데
You don't think I still care
내가 아직도
what they think, do you?
저 사람들을 신경 쓸 것 같아요?
If I really do something to you,
그리고 내가 정말 손을 쓰면
do you think they'll help you?
저 사람들이 할멈 편을 들 것 같아요?
Changning.
장녕
When I asked if you pushed Hutou just now,
언니가 방금 호두를 밀었냐고 물었을 때
why did you nod first and then shake your head?
왜 고개를 끄덕이다가 또 저었어?
I did push him.
밀긴 했는데
But he was too fat.
너무 뚱뚱해서
I couldn't move him.
안 밀렸어
He chased me,
날 쫓아오다가
fell down the stairs himself,
혼자 계단에서 굴러떨어져서
and broke his front teeth.
앞니가 부러진 거야
Hutou said you pushed him!
호두는 네가 민 거라고 했어
Shut up!
그 입 닥쳐요
I knew Hutou fell on his own.
내가 호두 혼자 넘어진 거라고 했잖아
Why did you push him?
왜 호두를 밀었는데?
He pulled my hair,
호두가 내 머리채를 잡고
snatched my candy,
사탕도 빼앗아 가고
threw rice water on me,
내가 재앙 덩어리의 동생이라
and called me a jinx's sister,
부정한 기운을 쫓아야 한다면서
saying I needed a splash of water to get rid of my bad luck.
나한테 쌀뜨물도 뿌렸어
You filthy old hag who deserves to be buried with no coffin!
이 할망구 곱게 못 죽을 줄 알게
Not only do you have a wicked tongue,
입 함부로 놀리면
you don't even do good deeds for your grandson.
그 업보가 다 손주에게 갈 걸세
Aren't you afraid the King of Hell
나중에 죽어 저승 가서
will rip your tongue out after you die?
혀 뽑히는 게 두렵지도 않은가
How am I wicked?
내가 뭘 어쨌다고?
Did I kill her parents?
쟤 부모를 내가 죽였나?
Did I kill all those people who died in her family?
이 집 가족들을 내가 죽인 거냐고
Everyone in Lin'an knows
쟤가 재앙 덩어리인 거
she's a jinx!
임안 전체에 모르는 사람이 있나?
Only you and your husband,
임종 지켜줄 자식도 없는
who have no one to bury you when you die,
이 집 두 늙은이만
took in this whole cursed family.
저 재앙 덩어리 가족을 거둬주는 거지
Maybe one day,
언젠가 조씨댁도
she'll bring you to your death too.
쟤 때문에 화를 입을 걸세
If you ask me,
내가 볼 땐
the Fan family
번씨 가족이 하루빨리
should've gotten out of Xigu Lane long ago.
이 서고 골목에서 사라져야 해
Who knows when their enemies will come looking for them.
언제 원수가 들이닥칠지 누가 아나
-Why are you so mean? -If I'm going to jinx anyone to death,
- 말이면 다인 줄 아나? - 내가 재앙 덩어리면
you'll be the first one, you old hag.
할멈 같은 사람부터 죽일 거예요
Why should I leave Xigu Lane?
서고 골목을 떠나라고요? 내가 왜요?
If you're so scared, you leave.
무서우면 할멈이 꺼져요
And listen—
그리고 너
if you ever
앞으로
lay a finger on Fan Changning again,
번장녕의 머리카락 한 올이라도 건드리면
whichever hand you use, I'll cut it off.
손목을 잘라 버릴 줄 알아
You think I'm scared of you?
이런다고 내가 겁먹을 줄 알아?
Don't try to scare me.
어디서 협박이야?
Scare you?
협박이요?
I can chop a pig's trotter clean off with one stroke.
돼지 족발도 단칼에 자르는데
Your hand would be even easier.
네 손 자르는 건 더 쉽지
Left or right?
왼손이랑 오른손 중에
Which one do you want to keep?
어느 쪽을 남기고 싶어?
-How about neither? -Don't!
- 차라리 둘 다 없애줄게 - 이러지 마
Hutou!
호두
Hu...
호...
Grandma!
할머니
Karma!
인과응보야
This is instant karma!
이게 바로 인과응보일세
You saw that, right?
다들 봤지?
Changyu and I didn't touch this old woman.
나랑 장옥은 건드리지도 않았는데
She fell on her own.
저 할멈 혼자 넘어진 걸세
It was her! She kicked me!
장옥이 날 걷어찼네
Granny Kang,
강 할멈
we were all watching.
할멈 혼자 넘어지는 거
You fell on your own.
여기 있는 사람들 다 봤어요
You must have been too vicious with your words,
그렇게 입을 함부로 놀리니까
so heaven punished you.
천벌 받은 거예요
Exactly.
맞는 말이에요
It was this jinx! She jinxed me!
다 저 재앙 덩어리 때문이야
Get lost! Or I'll jinx you to death!
당장 꺼져요 나 때문에 죽기 싫으면
Granny Kang,
강 할멈
be careful.
조심하게
Or you may knock your teeth out.
그러다 넘어져서 앞니가 나가면
Don't blame Changyu for that too.
또 장옥 탓하지 말고
Changning.
장녕
in the future, if anyone bullies you outside,
앞으로 누가 괴롭히면
come back and tell me, alright?
집에 와서 언니한테 얘기해 알았지?
How about you...
새해까지
not wait for the New Year?
기다리지 말고
Just go now.
지금 떠나는 게 어때요?
Just because of a few words from others,
사람들 말 몇 마디에
you want to chase me away?
날 쫓아내는 거요?
My family's troubles
우리 집안일에
have already dragged you in twice.
두 번이나 휘말렸잖아요
You don't owe me anything anymore.
이제 나한테 빚진 것도 없으니
If you cut ties with us sooner,
일찌감치 우리랑 인연을 끊는 게
you'll be safer.
당신을 위해서도 좋아요
You believe that woman's words?
그 아낙네 말을 믿는 것이오?
No.
안 믿어요
I don't believe in fate,
난 운명을 믿지도 않고
nor in that nonsense about being a cursed star
평생 혼자 살 팔자니
who brings misfortune.
타고난 액운이니 하는 것도 믿지 않아요
I just think that those people
하지만 그 사람들이
won't let my family go easily,
날 가만두지 않을 거라는 건 분명해요
so I don't want to drag you down with us.
거기에 당신까지 끌어들이고 싶지 않아요
If you think you can push me away
날 위해서
just because it's for my own good,
나와 거리를 두려는 거라면
then what about Changning?
장녕은 어쩔 거요?
Are you going to cut ties with her too?
동생과도 거리를 둘 거요?
I can't.
안 돼요
She's too young.
장녕은 아직 너무 어려서
I have to keep her with me.
내가 보살펴야 해요
So,
그러니까
you're only driving me away, is that it?
나만 쫓아내겠다는 거군
You're not the type to take an insult lying down.
당신도 당하고만 사는 성격은 아니니
If someone splashes water on you,
누가 괴롭히면
just teach them a lesson right then and there.
그 자리에서 갚아주면 그만이오
There's a saying I once heard from Mr. Wang:
왕 아저씨가 전에
"The law does not punish the masses."
법불책중이라는 말을 해 주신 적 있어요
It means that if a large group of people breaks the law,
많은 사람이 잘못을 저지르면
the authorities usually won't punish them all.
그 사람들 전부를 벌하지는 않는다는 뜻이에요
Now the whole town is gossiping about me
지금 마을 사람 전체가
behind my back.
날 손가락질하고 있어요
I might be able to deal with one of them,
내가 한 사람을 혼내줄 수는 있지만
but can I deal with them all?
모든 사람을 다 혼내줄 수는 없어요
[Young Xie Zheng]
[어린 사정]
[Young Wei Xuan]
[어린 위선]
Then have you ever heard of the saying
그럼
"make an example of someone"?
살계경후라는 말은 들어본 적 있소?
Human nature is evil.
인간의 본성은 악하오
If you're weak and easy to bully,
당신이 나약하고 별 볼 일 없는 사람이면
no matter how kind you are,
아무리 심성이 착해도
no one will help you.
아무도 도와주지 않을 것이오
But if you rise to power,
하지만 당신이 출세하면
even if you've done terrible things,
천벌 받을 짓을 해도
plenty of people will rush to flatter you.
모두가 당신에게 아첨할 거요
Superstitions are just meant to confuse people.
귀신에 관한 얘기는 본래 사람의 마음을 현혹하는 거요
Like the candy that hit Granny Kang just now—
강 할멈한테 날아간 그 사탕도
in her eyes,
그 할멈한테는
it was just a ghost playing tricks.
귀신 장난처럼 보이겠지
You can say these things to me,
나한테 이런 말 하는 건 상관없지만
but if you start distancing yourself
이 일 때문에
from Mr. Zhao and Mrs. Zhao because of it,
조씨 내외와 멀어지면
they will be heartbroken.
그분들이 서운해하실 거요
Then take what I said earlier
방금은
as a moment of impulse.
내가 너무 충동적이었어요
Please stay.
가지 말고 여기 남아요
So it's up to you
내가 가라면 가고
whether I leave or stay, huh?
남으라면 남는 사람인 줄 아시오?
You've got some nerve.
배짱이 대단하군
Don't be mad.
화내지 마요
The candy I bought you wasn't meant for that.
그러라고 사준 사탕인 줄 알아요?
You should have gone and found some pebbles.
돌멩이도 많은데
Candy is expensive.
왜 비싼 사탕으로 그런 짓을 해요?
♪ The scenery is as clear as me ♪
♪ 이 자연은 나처럼 평온하고 ♪
It was not worth it.
돈 아깝게
♪ With very pale colors ♪
♪ 은은한 빛깔은 ♪
♪ Just like the outline in the mirror ♪
♪ 거울에 비친 모습 같아 ♪
♪ I think that's me, being naive ♪
♪ 바보 같은 날 떠올리게 해 ♪
♪ Unlocking my heart ♪
♪ 내 마음 깊은 곳 ♪
I never had the chance to ask before.
늘 궁금했는데
♪ I hid you in my soul ♪
♪ 내 영혼에 널 숨겼어 ♪
Why did you become an armed escort and risk your life?
왜 목숨 걸고 표사 일을 해요?
Because...
왜냐하면
♪ The moon is as quiet as me ♪
♪ 달빛은 나처럼 조용해 ♪
there are things I simply must do.
반드시 해야 할 일이 있기 때문이오
Just like how
당신이
♪ The light shines ♪
♪ 빛무리는 ♪
you want to keep running your father's butcher shop.
아버지의 푸줏간을 계속 운영하고 싶어 하는 것처럼
♪ It illuminates the turbulence in my heart ♪
♪ 마음속 얼룩을 비추고 ♪
My father
우리 아버지가
♪ It seems to be the fire of love ♪
♪ 사랑의 불꽃은 흔들려 ♪
also had unfinished business.
마치지 못한 일을
♪ Just a few sparks ♪
♪ 얼마간 ♪
I want to finish it for him.
내가 이어서 하고 싶은 거요
♪ Let me hide in your heart ♪
♪ 네 마음속에 숨어 있게 해 줘 ♪
So your family ran an escort agency?
집안에서 표국을 운영하셨어요?
And you were the Young Master?
그럼 당신은 표국 도련님이었네요
♪ I pray that our love ♪
♪ 부디 우리 사랑이 ♪
♪ Will never end ♪
♪ 둘로 쪼개지지 않길 ♪
Rebuilding an escort agency costs a lot of money.
표국을 다시 운영하려면 돈이 많이 들 텐데
♪ It's worth my foolishly waiting ♪
♪ 평생을 미련하게 ♪
♪ For a lifetime ♪
♪ 기다릴 수 있어 ♪
When I have some money to spare,
나중에 형편이 좋아지면
I can help you out.
조금 보태 줄게요
♪ Clear and quiet as me ♪
♪ 나처럼 평온하게 나처럼 조용하게 ♪
No need.
괜찮소
I haven't repaid you
목숨을 살려준 은혜를
for saving my life yet.
아직 다 갚지도 못했는데
♪ So what if we encounter difficulties? ♪
♪ 가시밭길을 만나도 괜찮아 ♪
That's a completely different matter.
그건 다른 문제죠
♪ I pray that our love will not be like sand ♪
♪ 다른 모양의 사랑 ♪
When you agreed to marry into my family,
데릴사위로 들어와 준 거로
♪ Slipping into the sea ♪
♪ 그 알갱이가 바다로 들어가길 ♪
we were already even.
이미 정리 끝났어요
♪ I'd rather use this life ♪
♪ 이번 생에는 ♪
♪ To guard our love forever ♪
♪ 오래도록 사랑을 지킬래 ♪
You want to be even with me?
나랑 끝내고 싶소?
♪ Clear and quiet as me ♪
♪ 나처럼 평온하게 나처럼 조용하게 ♪
That's not what I meant.
전 그런 뜻이 아니에요
♪ Why do we need to seek cause and effect ♪
♪ 이유도 결말도 중요치 않아 ♪
We've known each other for so long,
우리가 알고 지낸 지도 꽤 오래됐는데
yet I still don't know when your birthday is.
당신 생일이 언제인지도 모르고 있군
My birthday is easy to remember.
내 생일은 기억하기 쉬워요
It's 2 days after the Lantern Festival.
정월 대보름 이틀 뒤거든요
The holiday spirit is still strong then.
그때쯤이면 명절 분위기가 한창이라
It's very lively.
시끌벅적해요
What do you want?
갖고 싶은 거 있소?
I want my family all together,
온 가족이 무탈하게
safe and sound.
함께했으면 좋겠어요
And if in the spring,
봄에
I could keep another litter of piglets, that would be even better.
새끼 돼지들을 키울 수 있으면 더 좋고요
[Capital]
[도성]
Your Majesty, I have a proposal.
폐하, 아뢸 말씀이 있사옵니다
Grand Tutor, please go ahead.
얘기해 보시오, 태부
Your Majesty,
폐하
the weather has been erratic this year.
올해는 비가 많이 내리지 않아
The land is barren, and the crops have failed.
가뭄이 들어 곡식이 익지 않았사옵니다
In this year of disaster,
이런 흉년에도
if we still transport grain to the front line,
비축한 식량을 전선으로 보낸다면
I fear it will cause a refugee crisis
유민이 들끓고
and shake the foundation of the state.
사직의 근간이 흔들릴까 심히 저어되옵니다
Your Majesty, I implore you
간청하옵건대
to revoke the restoration order for the front line.
전선의 재정비 명령을 거두어 주시옵소서
I humbly ask for Your Majesty's judgment.
헤아려주시옵소서, 폐하
The situation on the front line changes rapidly.
전선의 전황은 시시각각 변하는 법
Even the Marquis of Wu'an has fallen in battle.
무안후마저 전장에서 목숨을 잃었소
Provisions before a great battle are of the utmost importance.
전투에서 가장 중요한 것이 군량인데
How can we easily revoke the order?
그걸 어찌 쉽게 거둔단 말이오
After years of war,
오래된 전쟁으로
the treasury is now empty and cannot bear the burden.
국고가 바닥나서 더는 감당하기 어려운 형편입니다
If the treasury is empty, levy grain locally
국고가 비었으면 현지에서 군량을 징수하여
to solve the urgent need.
급한 불을 끄고
After we pacify Chongzhou,
숭주를 평정한 후에
we can return it to the people.
다시 백성들에게 돌려주면 그만이오
It is deep winter now, and the end of the year is approaching.
지금은 한겨울이고 연말이 다가오는데
The people's surplus grain is not enough to fill their own stomachs.
백성들의 남은 양식은 배도 못 채울 정도입니다
Levying grain locally?
그런데 현지에서 군량을 징수한다면
Prime Minister Wei,
위 승상은
are you not worried
민란이 일어날까
that it will incite a civil uprising?
걱정되지도 않으십니까?
The front line is engulfed in flames of war,
전장에서는 포화가 빗발치고
and our soldiers are fighting bloody battles.
군사들은 피 흘리며 싸우고 있소
Provisions are the lifeline of the army.
군량은 군의 명줄과 같아서
How can they go a day without them?
단 하루도 부족하면 안 되오
If the enemy takes this chance to march south and breach our cities,
그 기회에 적군이 남쪽으로 쳐들어와 성이 함락된다면
I fear it will bring disaster and ruin to our nation.
나라에 큰 화를 부를 것이오
Grand Tutor,
태부 혼자서
do you dare to bear such a heavy responsibility alone?
이 모든 걸 감당할 수 있겠소?
Surely, Grand Tutor Li,
이 태부도
you do not wish to repeat the tragedy of 16 years ago,
16년 전
when provisions failed to reach Jinzhou City,
근주성에 군량이 부족하여
leading to its massacre?
성이 함락되었던 과거를 되풀이하고 싶지는 않을 거요
Prime Minister Wei is farsighted.
위 승상은 신중하고 혜안을 가지고 있으니
He is truly the most loyal subject of Great Yin.
실로 우리 대윤의 으뜸가는 충신이라 할 만하오
[Diligent and Virtuous]
[근정친현]
Prime Minister Wei is loyal and righteous.
충의로우십니다, 위 승상
[Wei Residence]
[위부]
Uncle,
숙부님
when I grow up, I want to be like my father,
저도 커서 아버지처럼
fighting on the battlefield.
전장을 누빌 거예요
[Mrs. Wei]
[위 부인]
Prime Minister.
승상 나리
Come in.
들어오시오
Prime Minister, please have some ginseng tea.
인삼차 좀 드세요
Have Zheng's remains
사정의 시신은
still not been found?
아직도 못 찾았나요?
This child is of the Wei family's bloodline.
그 아이는 위가의 핏줄을 이어받았고
And he was raised with such care by you.
어릴 적부터 나리께서 정성으로 가르쳤잖아요
They say a maternal uncle is like a second father.
옛말에 외숙부는 아버지나 다름없다는데
It's such a pity that he died like this.
이리 허망하게 가 버리니 실로 안타깝습니다
Please take care of yourself, Prime Minister.
부디 옥체를 보중하세요
-And Xuan... -Please go back.
- 위선은... - 돌아가시오, 부인
I spoke out of turn.
제가 괜한 말씀을 드렸네요
I beg your forgiveness, Prime Minister.
부디 너그러이 헤아려 주세요
I shall take my leave.
그럼 이만 물러가겠습니다
Prime Minister,
승상 나리
He Jingyuan, Governor of Jizhou,
제주목 하경원이
has sent a brocade box by fast horse.
급히 금합를 보내왔습니다
[To Prime Minister Wei of Great Yin]
[대윤 위 승상 친전]
He has always been cautious.
하경원은 신중한 자였지
[To Wei Qilin]
[위기림 친전]
To General Suituo,
수탁 장군에게
Jinzhou is in critical danger.
근주가 위급합니다
I must return to the capital for an urgent matter.
저는 급한 사정으로 도성에 돌아가야 하는지라
Therefore, I am sending my household general, Wei Qilin,
가문의 장수 위씨 기림에게
to request immediate reinforcements with the Tiger Tally
호부를 지니게 하여 지원을 요청하는 바이니
to resist Beijue together
함께 북궐을 막고
and save Crown Prince Chengde.
승덕 태자를 위기에서 구해 주십시오
General, Wei Yan.
중랑장 위엄
Eighth day of the fifth month, the 26th year of Taikang.
태강 26년 5월 8일
It seems He Jingyuan
하경원 이자가
is using his own life as leverage
제 목숨을 담보로
to make me spare the two daughters of that traitor.
배신자의 두 딸을 살려두라 협박하는군
He Jingyuan is so bold.
참으로 대담하네요
Prime Minister, you shouldn't have been soft-hearted back then
그때 마음이 약해지셔서
and stopped searching for Wei Qilin's body.
위기림의 시신을 찾는 걸 포기하는 게 아니었습니다
Zheng's
사정이
sudden investigation into the Jinzhou massacre
갑자기 근주 참안을 조사한 것도
must have been instigated by someone with ulterior motives.
분명 누군가 사주한 거겠지
Now,
이제
even He Jingyuan goes against my orders.
하경원까지 내 뜻을 거스르는구나
Why don't you let me
차라리 소인이
go and get rid of He Jingyuan?
하경원을 제거하는 것이 어떻겠습니까
The battle in Chongzhou is critical right now.
지금 숭주 전투에서 어려움을 겪고 있는데
If I lose a weapon like He Jingyuan,
하경원이라는 칼마저 잃으면
the Northwest will be in peril.
서북 지역이 위험에 빠질 것이다
I see.
알겠습니다
Forget it.
됐다
They are just two girls.
고작 계집아이 둘일 뿐이니
[To Wei Qilin]
[위기림 친전]
Let them live.
살려두어도
How much trouble can they possibly cause?
아무런 파장도 일으키지 못할 테지
Lord Li?
이 공자
[Fill Your Belly]
[배불리 먹자]
Your husband is not home today?
낭군은 안 계시오?
He went out on business.
일 때문에 나갔어요
Do you need him for something, My Lord?
제 낭군에게 볼일이 있나요?
Just asking casually.
그냥 물어본 거요
By the way,
참
regarding the case involving your family,
댁에서 일어났던 사건이
I have figured out everything.
어찌 된 것인지 알아보았소
Who did it?
누구 짓입니까?
The Qingzhou Government Office found that the attacks on your family
제주부의 조사에 따르면 댁이 여러 차례 습격당한 건
stemmed from an escort mission your father undertook years ago.
낭자의 아버님이 과거에 운반하셨던 표와 관련이 있소
Rumor has it that it involved a treasure map
들리는 소문에는 전대 황실에서 남긴
left by the previous dynasty's royal family.
보물 지도 한 장이라고 하오
Over a decade ago,
십여 년 전
everyone in the escort agency was killed.
표국 사람 전원이 살해당하고
Only your father survived.
낭자의 아버님만이 겨우 목숨을 건져
That was why he could settle down here in Lin'an Town all these years.
임안진에서 몇 해 동안 무사히 지내신 거요
After the turmoil in Chongzhou,
숭주 전란 이후
the treasure map was brought up again.
다시 보물 지도에 관한 이야기가 퍼졌고
The bandits from Qingfeng Stronghold tracked down your father,
청풍채의 산적들이 아버님의 행방을 알아내
which is why they repeatedly attacked your home—
그 보물 지도를 손에 넣기 위해
to get that treasure map.
여러 번 댁에 쳐들어온 거요
Treasure map?
보물 지도라니요
I've never heard my parents mention it.
부모님께선 한 번도 그런 말씀 안 하셨어요
Yes.
그렇소
So, rumors can be deadly.
뜬소문이 사람 잡는다는 말도 있지 않소
Why did Li Huaian make up such a lie
이회안은 왜 저런 거짓말을 지어내서
just to close the case?
사건을 종결시키려 하는 거지?
My parents...
제 부모님께서
died just because of a rumor?
고작 이런 뜬소문 때문에 목숨을 잃으셨단 말인가요?
A few days ago, the rebels in Chongzhou announced
며칠 전 숭주 반란군 쪽에서
that they had already found the treasure map.
보물 지도를 찾았다는 소식이 흘러나왔소
The Qingfeng Stronghold bandits won't come to town anymore.
이제 청풍채 산적들이 마을에 찾아오는 일이 없을 테니
You can rest assured.
안심하시오
[Memorial Tablet of Meng Lihua] [Memorial Tablet of Fan Erniu]
[맹이화의 위패] [번이우의 위패]
If there's a chance to catch those bandits
만약 그 산적들을 잡아
and let my parents rest in peace,
부모님의 원한을 풀어드릴 수 있다면
I am at your command, My Lord.
공자가 시키는 건 뭐든지 할게요
[Fill Your Belly]
[배불리 먹자]
This is the relief fund sent
이것은 제주목 하 대인께서 민심을 헤아리시어
concern for the people. He specially appointed me to deliver it.
본관에게 전하라 명하신 무휼금이오
Is it all for me?
이걸 전부 다 저한테 주시는 거예요?
For those who suffered at the hands of the Qingfeng Stronghold bandits
청풍채 산적들 때문에
and lost family members,
가족을 잃은 사람들에게
the government has issued consolation money.
전부 위로금을 지급했소
It's not just your family.
낭자에게만 주는 게 아니오
The standard is 10 taels per person.
피해자 한 명당 열 냥씩
Here is 30 taels of silver.
은자 삼십 냥이니
Please accept it.
받으시오
Dry weather!
밤이 깊고 날이 건조하니
Beware of fire!
불조심하십시오
It's flying over!
날아왔어
Changyu,
언니
you talked in your sleep again last night.
어젯밤에 또 잠꼬대한 거 알아?
What did I say?
뭐라고 했는데?
You said you were afraid the spices from out of town weren't authentic.
외지에서 들어온 향신료는 별로라고 했어
You said,
또
"Five spices aren't enough, we need six."
오향은 부족하니 육향을 더해야 한댔어
Then you said that if Zheng left,
그리고 오라버니가 떠나면
you'd never find such a handsome husband again.
다시는 이렇게 잘생긴 낭군을 못 찾을 거라는 말도 했어
Keep your voice down.
목소리 낮춰
Changyu,
언니
we don't have to move anymore?
우리 이제 이사 안 가도 되는 거야?
But I already told the others in the village
마을 사람들한테
that we were moving.
우리 이사 간다고 다 얘기했는데
It's so embarrassing not to move now.
이제 와서 안 가면 창피하니까
Can we move out for a little while,
잠깐만 이사했다가
then move back?
다시 돌아오면 안 돼?
That would count as moving.
그것도 이사한 셈이잖아
Why are you so smart?
어쩜 이렇게 똑똑하지?
How about this?
그러지 말고
Tell them
친구들한테
we don't have to move anymore,
우리 이사 안 간다고 말하고
and give them some candy.
사탕을 나누어 주면
Then they won't laugh at you.
아무도 안 놀릴 거야
Changyu,
언니
when will you go back to sleep with Zheng?
언제 오라버니랑 같이 잘 거야?
You're squeezing into my small bed every day.
이 좁은 침대에서 매일 같이 자려니까
It's hard for me to even turn over.
너무 불편해
Mrs. Zhao says
아주머니가 그러셨는데
that a husband and wife should sleep together for life.
부부는 평생 같이 자야 한대
What?
왜 그래?
Are you sick of me already?
벌써 이 언니가 귀찮아?
I don't care.
몰라
I want to sleep with you.
난 너랑
For a lifetime!
평생 같이 잘 거야
How dare you be sick of me!
내가 귀찮아?
Take that!
내가 귀찮냐고
Are you still sick of me?
계속 귀찮아할 거야?
-No! -Are you?
- 안 그럴게 - 계속 귀찮아할래?
You're not, are you?
이제 안 귀찮지?
I yield.
내가 졌어
Beg for mercy, quickly!
얼른 항복해
Changyu!
언니
All you do is eat.
먹기만 하고
You're getting so fat.
이렇게 살이 쪄서
I wonder if you can still fly.
날 수는 있겠어?
Go now.
가 봐
[Xigu Lane]
[서고 골목]
Let's go.
가자
Morning, Mrs. Fan.
번 낭자, 좋은 아침이오
Morning.
좋은 아침이에요
Lord Li?
이 공자
Why are you at the Song's house?
왜 송가 댁에 계세요?
[Xigu Lane]
[서고 골목]
I rented a vacant house from a broker.
빈집을 하나 빌렸는데
When I got here, I realized it was opposite your home.
와 보니 낭자 댁 맞은편이더군
So this family is named Song?
이 집 주인이 송씨였나 보오
Aren't you going back to Jizhou?
제주로 안 돌아가세요?
I promised I would find
낭자의 부모님을 해친 범인을
the murderer of your parents.
찾아주겠다고 했으니
I must keep my word.
약조를 지켜야 하지 않겠소
Lord Li?
이 공자
To catch the murderer, Lord Li
범인을 잡기 위해
decided to stay for a while.
당분간 임안에 머물기로 하셨대요
And he even rented Song Yan's house.
마침 송연네 집을 빌렸지 뭐예요
Isn't that a coincidence?
신기하죠?
What a coincidence indeed.
정말 신기하구려
I won't disturb you two.
그럼 방해하지 않겠소
What's wrong?
왜 그래?
The falcon is gone.
준준이 없어졌어
Maybe the lid wasn't closed tightly last night.
어젯밤에 뚜껑을 제대로 안 닫았나 보구나
After its wings healed, it flew away on its own.
날개가 다 나아서 혼자 날아갔나 봐
This falcon has parents of its own.
그 새도 부모님이 있을 테니
It needs to go home to find them.
집으로 돌아간 걸 거야
Don't cry.
울지 마
There's nothing we can do.
어쩔 수 없잖아
The falcon has a family too.
준준도 가족에게 돌아가야지
Don't cry.
울지 마
It will fly back.
다시 올 거야
Can you pinky-promise me for the falcon?
오라버니가 준준 대신 약속해 줄 수 있어요?
You're going to leave sooner or later,
당신은 언젠가 떠날 거죠?
aren't you?
그렇죠?
In my current situation,
내 지금 처지에
loving someone
누군가를 좋아한다면
only puts them in danger.
그건 그 사람을 해치는 거야
People
사람은
are not deities who cut off emotions and desires.
모든 욕망과 감정을 끊어버린 신선이 아니라
It's hard to control
마음이 시키는 일을
your feelings.
자제하기 어려워
Don't coax her.
달래줄 필요 없어요
Changning is just a bit lonely.
외로워서 그러는 거니까
I'll buy a cage of chicks in the spring.
봄이 되면 병아리 몇 마리 사주면 돼요
With new playmates, she'll forget the falcon.
새 친구가 생기면 그 매는 잊어버릴 거예요
In the spring,
봄이 되면
I'll buy you a big cage of chicks, okay?
언니가 병아리 잔뜩 사줄게 어때?
No. I want the falcon.
싫어, 준준이 보고 싶어
You don't want that?
떼쓰지 마
I wasn't coaxing her.
달래주는 거 아니오
To fully tame a falcon,
매를 길들이려면
you have to let it fly first.
마지막에 놓아주어야 하오
Only one that returns
그래서 다시 돌아와야만
is truly tamed.
비로소 완전히 길들여진 거요
But there's no guarantee it will come back.
안 돌아올 수도 있는 거잖아요
[Aspiring to the Clouds]
[심향운단]
So you're really not leaving Lin'an?
정말 안 떠나는 거야?
I was so happy when I heard the news
그 소식을 듣고
that I couldn't sleep all night.
너무 기뻐서 밤새 한숨도 못 잤어
I'll show you something.
보여줄 것이 있어
I've been preparing it for a long time.
내가 특별히 오랫동안 준비한 거야
-Come on. -What is it?
- 자 - 뭔데요?
What are you doing?
뭐 하는 거예요?
Look.
봐
The auspicious time has arrived!
길시요
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[번씨네 고기조림]
[Braised Pork Belly] [Braised Pig's Ear]
[돼지고기 조림] [돼지귀 조림]
Bravo!
좋소
Pray to the God of Wealth,
재물신께
and may your business prosper!
돈 많이 벌게 해달라고 빌어
What's wrong?
왜 그래요?
Nothing.
아무것도 아니야
Let's offer the incense.
향 올려
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[번씨네 고기조림]
Okay.
좋소
What would you like to eat?
뭐 드릴까요?
Your meat smells delicious.
향이 정말 좋네요
I want a piece that's not too fatty.
안 느끼한 부위로 줘요
None of them is too fatty. They're all good.
전부 안 느끼하고 맛있어요
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[번씨네 고기조림]
Pick a big one.
큰 덩어리로 주세요
Okay.
네
I'll weigh it for you.
달아 드릴게요
Come back often.
또 오세요
Okay.
네
Changyu?
장옥이구나
It's me, it's me.
네, 저예요
Your shop has been closed for a while.
번가네 푸줏간이 문을 닫아서
We couldn't buy braised meat anywhere.
한동안 고기 조림을 살 곳이 없었는데
Turns out you came to Yixiang Restaurant to make it.
일향루에서 장사하고 있었구나
Mrs. Fan
번 낭자는
is partnering with Yixiang Restaurant now.
이제 일향루와 손잡고
She'll sell exclusively here from now on.
앞으로는 여기서만 판매할 거예요
Ma'am, feel free to come by anytime if you like it.
입에 맞으시면 자주 찾아 주세요
Changyu's pork used to come
전에 장옥이네 가게에서 돼지고기를 사면
with free offal.
부속을 덤으로 줬었는데
Then I won't be polite.
그럼 사양 안 할게요
Look at this.
이것 좀 보세요
I... this...
그게...
This time...
이제는...
Well, this time...
이번에는 안...
Changyu's braised meat
장옥이 전에 만들었던 고기 조림은
used to be home-style.
집에서 먹던 익숙한 맛이지만
Now that she's with Yixiang Restaurant,
저희 일향루와 협력하면서
the ingredients and recipe are upgraded.
재료와 양념 비법까지 다 개선했어요
Let alone offal,
부속은 말할 것도 없고
even the stock is pricier.
조림 국물까지 전보다 훨씬 귀해졌답니다
Well,
그래요?
then how can we common folk afford that?
그럼 우리 같은 백성은 못 사 먹겠네요
Forget it.
그냥
I'll look elsewhere.
다른 가게에 가 봐야겠어요
We are opening today,
오늘은 개업일이니까
so we want to start on a lucky note.
좋은 의미로
If you
아주머니께서
can bring us 5 customers in the future,
손님 다섯 분을 데려오면
you'll get a 20 percent discount.
8할로 해드리고
25 percent off for 10 customers.
열 분을 데려오면 7할 반
And 30 percent off for 20. How about that?
스무 분을 데려오면 7할에 해드릴게요
Alright.
알겠어요
Changyu,
장옥
pick two good pieces of meat for me.
좋은 고기 두 점만 골라주렴
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[번씨네 고기조림]
It's my husband's birthday today.
오늘이 우리 영감 생일이거든
Okay.
알겠어요
I guarantee it'll be delicious and generous.
맛도 좋고 양도 푸짐해요
That piece.
저걸로 줘
I didn't want to offer free offal before,
전에 장사할 때도 덤으로 주기 싫었는데
and the customers were unwilling to accept it.
손님들이 언짢아해서 어쩔 수 없이 드렸거든요
You just said a few words,
그런데 언니 말 몇 마디에
and they rushed to give us money.
불티나게 팔리네요
Qianqian, you're really amazing at doing business.
장사 수완이 정말 대단해요
Undercutting isn't business.
가격을 내리는 건 장사가 아니야
Mutual benefit is what business is all about.
장사라면 이득을 봐야지
The great man is he who is in harmony,
대인이 된 자는
in his attributes, with heaven and earth;
천지와 그 덕을 같이하고
in his brightness, with the sun and moon;
일월과 그 밝음을 같이하며
in his orderly procedure, with the four seasons;
사계절과 그 순서를 같이하고
and in his relation to what is fortunate and what is calamitous,
귀신과 그 길흉을 같이하나니
He naturally—
이는 본래...
Your Lordship honors me with your presence.
후작 나리께서 친히 행차하셨으니
My wait was not in vain.
기다림이 헛되지 않았네요
Tell me. What is your purpose in coming to the Fan family?
무슨 목적을 가지고 번가에 찾아온 것이오?
I came to the Fan family
번가에 찾아간 것은
only to see you, Your Lordship.
후작 나리를 만나기 위함이었습니다
We have known each other since childhood
나리와 저는 어릴 적부터 함께 자랐고
and both learned martial arts from General He.
하 장군 밑에서 같이 무공을 배웠지만
Since the conflict between the Li and Wei,
이가와 위가의 사이가 틀어진 이후로
we've been avoiding each other.
서로를 멀리했습니다
It has been
그게 벌써
over a decade, hasn't it?
십수 년이나 되었네요
I am curious now.
자네가 지금
Are you a Li
이씨인지
or a Wei?
아니면 위씨인지 그것이 궁금하군
I only serve Great Yin
전 오직 대윤과
and the people.
백성을 위할 뿐입니다
What about you, Your Lordship?
그러는 후작 나리는
Which side are you on now?
지금 어느 편입니까?
Anyone can say
입에 발린 말은
pretty words.
누구나 할 수 있지
I have always
나는
only served myself.
나 자신만을 위하오
The conflict between Li and Wei has become chaotic.
태부와 승상의 싸움으로 혼란스러운 시국에
And you intend to establish your own faction in the future.
후작 나리께서 굳이 독립하겠다는 건
Do you wish to make this chaos even worse?
상황을 더 복잡하게 만들겠다는 겁니까?